Finding Aid for International Order of King’s Daughters and Sons, Michigan Branch records, 1897-2008
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
International Order of King’s Daughters and Sons, Michigan Branch records 1897-2008, 1974-1992
International Order of King’s Daughters and Sons. Michigan Branch.
1 oversize folders
8 oversize volumes
7.3 linear feet (in 8 boxes)
93818 Bk 2
Minutes, correspondence, reports, programs, financial records and photographs documenting statewide service activities and programs of various county circles; also photograph albums and scrapbooks.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The records were donated by the Michigan Branch of International Order of the King’s Daughters and Son (donor no. 7725 ) in various accessions.
No further additions to the records are expected.
The record group is open to research.
The International Order of the King's Daughters and Sons was originally founded January 13, 1886, as the King's Daughters. The organization was incorporated in 1888 as the Order of the King's Daughters, and in 1891 the present name was adopted. The Michigan Branch was founded ca. 1896.
The Order, which has branches in the United States and Canada, is an interdenominational service organization. Membership is open to anyone who shares the Order's aims and purposes and who professes him- or herself a Christian. The Order's purpose is to participate in, and support, religious, educational, and philanthropic endeavors while training individuals (both members and non-members alike) for leadership in Christian service. The Order's branches support ministries for the aging, the handicapped, and the underprivileged through homes, hospitals, youth camps, day care centers, scholarship programs and donation drives. In Michigan, for example, the Order founded and ran the Hospital School for children at the University of Michigan Hospital.
Throughout its history, the Order has realized its goal of educating for Christian service by offering scholarships. One scholarship program provided financial aid for Native American students, overseas students, and students interested in training for the ministry and other forms of Christian service. A second scholarship program provided financial assistance for students in health sciences programs. A third financial aid program, the Chautauqua Scholarship Program, began in 1920 and provided funding for young adults who wished to participate in courses offered at the Order's own Chautauqua Institution. This institution offered "self-enrichment" and Christian leadership courses, and was housed in a compound consisting of a chapel, a Fellowship Hall, and three houses. The Chautauqua Institution accommodated forty-three students and a full staff.
The basic unit of the Order is the circle, which generally consists of women in an individual church congregation. Circles are organized into county-wide branches, which are in turn organized into state-wide branches. The Order's official publication is the Silver Cross Magazine.
In 2008, the organization voted to disband.
The records of the Michigan Branch of the International Order of the King's Daughters and Sons have come to the library in multiple accessions. The record group is comprised of the following series: Minutes, Financial Records, Organizational Leadership Membership, Camp Missaukee, Conventions, Service and Ministry Activities, Background and Published Material, County Branches, Photographs, and Scrapbooks.
Subjects:
International Order of the King's Daughters and Sons. Michigan Branch.; Women--Michigan--Societies and clubs.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Camp Missaukee (Lake City, Mich.); Camps--Michigan--Missaukee County.; Children.; Missaukee County (Mich.)
Genre Terms:
Photographs.; Scrapbooks.
- Minutes
  - Membership list and Report of State Convention 1897-1899 (Box 1)
  - Executive Board Meetings
    - November 1909-June 1914 (Box 1)
    - November 1915-November 1923 (Box 1)
      (include minutes of the 17th Annual Convention, October 1913)
    - June 1924-May 1930 (Box 1)
    - October 1930-April 1933 (Box 1)
    - October 1933-October 1936 (Box 1)
    - June 1937-October 1937 (Box 1)
  - Board Meetings and Conventions
    - 1938-1939 (Box 1)
    - 1940 (Box 1)
    - 1941 (Box 1)
    - 1945-1946 (Box 1)
    - 1947-1949 (Box 1)
    - 1950-1952 (Box 1)
    - 1953-1955 (Box 1)
    - 1956-1959 (Box 1)
    - 1960-1965 (Box 1)
    - 1966-1967 (Box 1)
    - 1969-1970 (Box 1)
    - 1971-1972 (Box 1)
    - 1973 (Box 1)
    - 1974-1975 (Box 1)
    - 1976-1979 (Box 1)
    - 1980-1983 (Box 1)
    - 1984-1987 (Box 1)
    - 1991-2001 (Box 2)
    - 2002-2004 (Box 2)
    - 2005-2009 (Box 2)
- Financial Records
  - Letter regarding King's Daughters Mortgage Application 1956 (Box 2)
  - Treasurer's Reports
    - 1937-1942 (Box 2)
    - 1945-1952 (Box 2)
    - 1953-1957 (Box 2)
    - 1962-1964 (Box 2)
    - 1965-1970 (Box 2)
    - 1971-1977 (Box 2)
    - 1999-2002 (Box 2)
  - Financial Reports
    - 1978-1979 (Box 2)
    - 1981-1985 (Box 2)
    - 1997-2006 (Box 2)
  - Financial Statements
    - 1988-1990, 1992-1997 (Box 2)
    - 2001, 2003-2005 (Box 2)
  - Disbursements and Budget Comparisons 1988-1996 (scattered dates) (Box 2)
  - Financial ledger 1963-1977 (Box 2)
    (state-level record book of individual circles' finances; includes record of active/disbanded circles, memorial gifts)
  - Michigan Non-Profit Corporations Report 1927 (Box 2)
  - Non-Profit Corporation Form 1949-2008 (scattered dates) (Box 2)
  - Tax-Exempt Status 1988-2003 (Box 2)
    (scattered dates; form 1023 and correspondence)
  - Stock documentation 1976-1985 (scattered dates) (Box 2)
  - Elizabeth MacGregor Fund 1965-1979 (scattered dates) (Box 2)
  - Elizabeth MacGregor Fund 1983-1998 (Box 2)
    (scattered dates; includes related correspondence)
- Organizational Leadership
  - Articles of Incorporation 1929 (Box 2)
  - Certificate of Amendment to the Articles of Incorporation 1983 (Box 2)
  - By-laws and Constitution 1963-2004 (scattered dates) (Box 2)
  - List of Officers 1973-1983, 2007/08 (scattered dates) (Box 2)
  - Official Board Roster 1983-2002 (scattered dates) (Box 2)
  - Information for Treasurers 1966, undated (Box 2)
  - County and Circle Presidents and Treasurers roster 1990-1991 (Box 2)
  - County and Circle Presidents and Treasurers roster 1999 (Box 2)
  - County and Circle Presidents and Treasurers roster 2001, undated (Box 2)
  - Official Board Roll Call 1987-2002 (scattered dates) (Box 2)
  - President's Reports 1970-1983 (scattered dates) (Box 2)
  - President's Reports 2000-2002 (Box 2)
  - Annual Reports
    - 1968 (Box 2)
    - 1971-1984 (scattered dates) (Box 2)
    - 1993-2000 (scattered dates) (Box 2)
  - Duties of the First Vice President 1984 (Box 2)
  - Report of the Second Vice President 1939 (Box 2)
  - Officers' Annual Reports
    - 1938 (Box 2)
    - 1966, 1970 (Box 2)
    - 1971-1976 (Box 2)
    - 1982-1985 (Box 2)
    - 1997 (Box 2)
  - Record books of organization officer: include convention reports, Camp Missaukee information, board meetings and program reports 1975-1983, 2 volumes (Box 3)
- Membership
  - Membership Lists
    - 1940-1949, 5 folders (Box 3)
    - 1964-1967, 5 folders (Box 3)
    - 2008 (Box 3)
  - List of Membership in Michigan Circles undated (Box 3)
  - Admission Service undated (Box 3)
  - Citation Records Forms 1985-1990, 2001 (Box 3)
  - Applications for Citation for Continuous Membership
    - 1984-1986 (Box 3)
    - 1987-1989 (Box 3)
    - 1990-1992 (Box 3)
  - Display volume containing circles, membership, citations and tributes circa 1946 (Box 3)
  - Services of Remembrance (Box 3)
  - Memorial Booklets, scattered dates (Box 3)
  - Roll of Deceased Members circa 1940 (Box 3)
  - Memorial Citation for Elizabeth MacGregor circa 1946 (Box 3)
  - "In Remembrance" Memorial Books 1957-2001 (Box 3)
  - "In Remembrance" Memorial Books 2001-2006 (Box 3)
- Camp Missaukee
  - Camp Inspections 1970, 1972-1975, undated (Box 4)
  - Budgets and Camp Needs
    - 1947-1955 (scattered dates) (Box 4)
    - 1964-1967 (Box 4)
    - 1971-1986 (Box 4)
  - Camp Committee Memos 1972-1974, 1977 undated (Box 4)
  - Camp Committee Minutes 1970-1979 (scattered dates) (Box 4)
  - Camp Committee Duties 1973-1975, undated (Box 4)
  - Camp Policies 1977, undated (Box 4)
  - Camp Reports 1939-1985 (scattered dates) (Box 4)
  - Correspondence 1939-1986 (scattered dates) (Box 4)
  - Donations 1972, 1974 undated (Box 4)
  - Evening Programs 1971-1974 (Box 4)
    (campfire songs, skits, and activities)
  - Tax Tribunal Situation 1983-1986 (scattered dates) (Box 4)
  - Sale of Property 1986 (Box 4)
  - Applications and Brochures 1954-1983 (scattered dates) and undated (Box 4)
  - Campers 1974-1976 (scattered dates) (Box 4)
  - Photographs--1982 Camp Staff (Box 4)
  - Newsletters 1970 (Box 4)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 4)
- Conventions
  - Report of the State Convention, Detroit, May 6th-7th 1897 (Box 4)
  - Convention Call 1927-2002 (scattered dates) (Box 4)
  - Convention Resolutions 1938 (Box 4)
  - Convention Memorials 1961-2000 (scattered dates) (Box 4)
  - State Convention Programs
    - 1925-1940 (Box 4)
      (lacking 1928 and 1932)
    - 1941-1955 (Box 4)
      (lacking 1945)
    - 1956-1970 (Box 4)
    - 1971-2008 (Box 4)
      (lacking 1975-1976, 1983, 2003, 2005 2007)
  - Convention Reports 1992-2001 (scattered dates) (Box 4)
  - Miscellaneous convention materials 1950-2002 (scattered dates) (Box 4)
  - State Branches' Response to Michigan Branch 94th Convention Call 1991-1992 (Box 4)
  - State Branches' Response to Michigan Branch 95th Convention Call 1993 (Box 4)
  - President's Correspondence 1983 (Box 4)
  - President's Correspondence, scattered dates (Box 4)
  - Correspondence 1984-2001 (scattered dates) (Box 4)
- Service and Ministry Activities
  - University Hospital School 1929-1983 (scattered dates) (Box 4)
  - C.S. Mott Children's Hospital 1975-2004 (scattered dates) (Box 4)
  - North American Indian Department 1965-2000 (scattered dates) (Box 4)
  - Around the World Department 1974-1979 (scattered dates) (Box 4)
  - Reports on Activities--Dorcas Home, Flint, MI 1938 (Box 4)
  - Blank Forms (Box 4)
    (for orders, donations, etc.)
  - Certificates of Appreciation 1995 (Box 4)
  - Certificate of Commendation (Folder 1)
  - Junior Circles 1930-1966 (scattered dates) (Box 4)
  - Devotional Themes 1991-1996 (scattered dates) (Box 4)
  - Spiritual Life reading lists and related correspondence 1983-2001 (scattered dates) (Box 4)
- Background and Published Material
  - Assorted materials regarding King's Daughters' background 1930-1998 (Box 5)
    (scattered dates; includes letter from Bill Clinton and KD background)
  - Informational booklets (Box 5)
  - Prayers, pledges, and hymns undated (Box 5)
  - Program to the Fourth General Convention, Detroit, Mich. June 10, 1938; also International Order members' directory, 2006 (Box 5)
  - News clippings (Box 5)
  - History of the International Order of The King's Daughters and Sons (various editions), 1931, 1951, 1970, 1986 (Vol. IV, 1970-1986), 5 volumes (Box 5)
- County Branch Records
  - General Information
    - Historical background 1993 (Box 5)
    - County Annual Reports
      - 1938 (Box 5)
      - 1939-1957 (scattered dates) (Box 5)
      - 1966-1970 (scattered dates) (Box 5)
      - 1971-1975 (scattered dates) (Box 5)
      - 1976-1977 (Box 5)
      - 1982-1984 (Box 5)
    - Various Circle Reports 1945-1946 (Box 5)
  - Genesee County
    - Genesee County 1966-1976 (Box 5)
    - Flint Opportunity Circle 1970-1975 (Box 5)
  - Iosco County
    - Iosco Happy Helpers Junior Circle minute book 1957 (Box 5)
  - Jackson County
    - County Branch History (Box 6)
    - County Directory 1954 (Box 6)
    - County Directory 1967 (Box 6)
    - County Board Meetings 1986-1990 (Box 6)
      (minutes and related material)
    - County Board Meetings 1991-1999 (Box 6)
    - County Convention and Board Meeting minutes 1953-1973 (Box 6)
      (bound volume)
    - County Convention and Board Meeting minutes 1973-1987 (Box 6)
    - Convention Programs 1946-1970 (scattered dates) (Box 6)
    - Convention Programs 1971-1983 (scattered dates) (Box 6)
    - County Convention lists of attendees 1969-1983 (Box 6)
    - News clippings 1960-1983 (scattered dates) (Box 6)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 6)
    - Evangeline Circle
      - Membership list and constitution 1932, undated (Box 6)
      - Program books 1936-1998 (scattered dates) (Box 6)
      - Correspondence 1941-1988 (scattered dates) (Box 6)
      - Scrapbook, 1959-1960 (Box 6)
        (includes membership list, minutes and photographs of members)
      - Scrapbook, 1932-1957 (Volume 2)
      - Scrapbook, 1969-1977 (Volume 6)
      - Fiftieth Anniversary 1982, 1992 (Box 6)
      - 60 Years Citation for Service circa 1992 (Box 6)
    - Scattergood Circle 1974-1975 (Box 6)
    - Silver Cross Circle, Scrapbook 1959-1966 (Box 6)
  - Macomb County
    - Miscellaneous 1966-1969 (Box 6)
  - Midland County
    - Membership booklets 1973-1982 (scattered dates) (Box 6)
    - County Annual Report 1968-1981 (scattered dates) (Box 6)
    - Letter to members 2008 (Box 6)
  - Saginaw County
    - County Annual Reports 1969-1985 (scattered dates) (Box 6)
    - County Convention programs 1950-1974 (scattered dates) (Box 6)
    - Bridgeport Circle 1972 (Box 6)
    - First Circle 1971-1972 (Box 6)
    - News clippings 1969-1972 (Box 6)
  - Shiawassee County
    - Governance 1923-1997 (scattered dates) (Box 8)
    - County Branch Annual Report 1955 (Box 8)
    - Circle Reports 1946-1973, undated (scattered dates) (Box 8)
    - County Convention programs 1966-1975 (scattered dates)
    - In His Name Circle meeting minutes (Box 8)
      - 1943-1953 (Box 8)
      - 1956-1964 (Box 8)
    - Jo's Operation Telephone Home 1968-1972 (scattered dates) (Box 8)
    - News clippings 1969-2002 (scattered dates) (Box 8)
    - Miscellaneous
    - Silver Cross Circle
      - By-laws and constitution 1958-1995 (scattered dates) (Box 8)
      - Account books
        - 1940-1952 (scattered dates) (Box 8)
        - 1950-1954 (Box 8)
        - 1994-2004 (Box 8)
      - Annual Reports 1988-2000 (Box 8)
      - Minutes and Attendance Rolls
        - 1986-2000, 14 folders (Box 8)
        - 2000-2005 (Box 8)
          (includes photos of 2000 Eshelman scholarship recipient)
      - Membership lists 1968-2003 (scattered dates) (Box 8)
      - Scholarship Recipients 1986-1997 (Box 8)
      - Scholarship Recipients 1999-2002 (Box 8)
      - Scholarship Recipients 2002-2003 (Box 8)
      - Scholarship Recipients 2004 (Box 8)
      - Legal documents pertaining to Eshelman Estate and Scholarship 1982, 1984 (Box 8)
      - 70 Years Citation for Service undated (Box 8)
        (includes photographs of circle members, dated 1992 and 2000)
      - Correspondence 1989-2004 (scattered dates) (Box 8)
  - Washtenaw County
    - King's Daughters, M.E. Church, [Ann Arbor]--Membership and Finances 1911-1923 (Box 8)
    - Phoebe Beal and Goodwill Circles 1948-2000 (Box 8)
    - Miscellaneous 1965-1993 (Box 8)
      (scattered dates; includes reports, county convention materials, misc.)
  - Wayne County
    - Convention programs 1969-1974 (Box 8)
    - Detroit Circles 1930-1993, undated (scattered dates) (Box 8)
    - Wayne County Circles, including Northville 1968-1978 (scattered dates) (Box 8)
- Photographs
  - Members, leaders, and activities 1900-1969 (scattered dates) (Box 7)
  - Albums
    - Camp Life 1952 (Box 7)
    - Camp Missaukee Memories 1968-1970 (Box 7)
    - 1970 (Box 7)
    - 1971 (Box 7)
      (2 folders)
- Scrapbooks
  - 1929-1950 (Volume 1)
  - 1937-1938 (Volume 3)
  - 1951-1958 (Volume 4)
  - 1958-1963 (Volume 5)
  - 1962-1975 (Volume 7)
  - 1977-1978 (Volume 8)